Finding Aid for Extension Service (University of Michigan) records, 1911-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Extension Service (University of Michigan) records 1911-1999
University of Michigan. Extension Service.
University of Michigan unit established in 1911 to advance culture in the state, assist local communities with technical knowledge, and acquaint faculty with local conditions through course offerings and lectures by university faculty and staff at sites around the state. Records include annual reports of extension activity from 1911 to 1980, director's files, committee minutes, special reports and surveys, and records of lectures and courses given.
87169 Bimu C470 2 UBImum C470
60.0 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 1660 ) came to the library in various acquisitions beginning in the 1950s. Periodic accessions are received.
The records are open for research with the exception of personnel files located in boxes 46-49 which are closed in accordance with university policy and applicable law.
The Extension Division of the University of Michigan was formally organized by the Board of Regents in 1911. The major purposes of the Extension Division were to serve the general cause of education and advancement of culture in the state, to provide local communities with the technical and experimental knowledge of the university faculty, and to acquaint members of the various faculties with local conditions throughout the state. The bylaws of the Extension Division also stated that only those areas of university activity which have their roots in campus programs may be carried throughout the state.
The first responsibility of the Extension Division was the management of the Educational Lecture Bureau. President H. B. Hutchins named William D. Henderson of the Physics Department as part-time director of this program. With the support of President Hutchins and the Board of Regents, the scope of the Extension Division's operations grew from the administration of lectures, to a small number of credit classes which began in Detroit in 1913, and then to a program that served nearly a dozen Michigan communities with lectures and credit courses by the mid-twenties.
In the period between 1935 and 1950 the Extension Service experienced tremendous growth. Enrollment increased from 3,500 to 21,000. The main reason for this increase was the opening of six regional offices throughout the state. The first of the offices was established in Detroit in 1935 at the university's Horace H. Rackham Educational Memorial Building. Later offices were set up in Grand Rapids, Flint, Saginaw, Ann Arbor, and Escanaba. The development of regional area offices made it possible to present and develop long-range programs in various fields.
In the post World War II era the Extension Service actively developed new programs and regional offices. Some of these programs flourished, e.g. music, art, gerontology, real estate, and firemanship training; others, the Worker's Educational Program for example, were abandoned. The credit courses offered through the Extension Service gradually became more oriented towards the graduate student. By 1980, nearly 95% of the credit courses offered through the Extension Service were for graduate credit.
The Extension Service was reduced by 90% in 1981. The report of the budget review subcommittee investigating the Extension Service unanimously recommended that the University of Michigan Extension Service should be discontinued as an administrative unit. This included the transfer of all off-campus instruction activities to the appropriate academic unit and the discontinuance or transfer of all credit-free activities.
The Extension Service has had five directors. The first, William D. Henderson, served as part-time director from 1912 to 1919. In 1919 he was appointed director and held that position until his retirement in 1937. Henderson was succeeded by Charles A. Fisher. Fisher had been the assistant director under Henderson and was the director of the Extension Service from 1937 until his death in 1948. Everett J. Soop became director in 1948 and served until his retirement in 1970. Alfred Storey, who had been assistant director, succeeded Soop. He retired from this position in 1989. Glenda Radine, director of the Department of Conferences and Institutes, was appointed as interim director. She served in this capacity until the Extension Service was reconfigured in 1995 and its activities incorporated into the Academic Outreach unit. Academic Outreach, created to manage non-traditional instruction programs and distance education, was dissolved in 1999.
The Firemanship Training Program
The Firemanship Training Program grew out of the Michigan Fire College that was begun in 1928 to train fire personnel in techniques of fire fighting. The Fire College found a permanent home at the University of Michigan in 1941. The following year, the Department of Extension Services in conjunction with the School of Education set up classes to train fire department instructors. Chief Wallace Gannon of the Muskegon Fire Department came to the school in 1942 to be the instructor for the year. He returned in 1946 and was full-time instructor until 1953. In 1943, the program was expanded to include off-campus courses in fire fighting techniques. The programs became very popular and from 1946 to 1960 over 15,000 fire fighters participated in these programs.
With demand rising for these programs, it was soon apparent that a permanent facility was needed where residential training could take place. A new facility was proposed in 1955 and the Civil Defense and Disaster Training Center was completed in 1959. Francis Hartman, who had been involved with the program from the beginning, became the first director of the new center and program. He was succeeded by Arthur Appel who retired in 1978, and was succeeded by Robert Schultz, former assistant director, in 1978.
The first residential fire school at the new facility was held August 17-28, 1959. This new building provided for even further expansion of the program. The courses offered were expanded to include three residential schools in fire training-- basic, intermediary, advanced--, a longer 240-hour academy, and numerous yearly conferences in the areas of arson control, fire chief training, industrial fire control, fire instruction, state property fire control, and civil defense training.
The 90% reduction in Extension Services in 1981 had its effect on the Firemanship Training Program. Money was no longer available to support the program as before and offerings and enrollments were declining. In 1991, the program was transferred to the Housing Division, Department of Conferences and Seminars. The last residential fire school was held in July 1992. The department continued to offer the various conferences and seminars until 1994 when they canceled all offerings except for a conference on fire control. The Civil Defense and Disaster Center is currently used by the Ann Arbor Fire Department as a substation.
Academic Outreach
In 1995, the Extension Service, as an independently functioning University department, was abolished and its services incorporated into Academic Outreach. This office was created to coordinate the University's increasingly varied efforts to extend its educational mission of teaching, research, and service beyond the University's residential campus. One of its major responsibilities is to find constructive ways to expand the University's learning environment through technology. The University of Michigan Virtual Campus and the Michigan Virtual Auto College are examples of several resultant programs. Academic Outreach was disbanded in 1999. Several of the unit's responsibilities were transferred to the Media Union as well as to other units on campus. (See University Record, February 22, 1999 "Media Union to Provide Learning Technology Support" for information on the dissolution of Academic Outreach.)
The records of the Extension Service are organized into six series: Director's Files, Central Files, Histories, Firemanship Training Program, Audio-Visual Material and Academic Outreach Files.
The records of the Extension Service document the university's efforts to extend its educational efforts beyond the campus. The records include annual reports of extension activity from 1911 to 1980, committee minutes, special reports and surveys, and records of lectures and courses given throughout the state. Topics include adult education, continuing education, work in several Michigan communities, and files relating to civil defense and disaster training, firemanship training, World War II management and science training programs, and gerontology. Documentation includes files of directors William Henderson, Charles A. Fisher, Everett J. Soop, and Alfred W. Storey. Of note are records of Charles Follo relating to extension work in the Upper Peninsula.
Subjects:
Adult education--Michigan.; Education--Michigan.; Fire prevention--Study and teaching.; University extension--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Extension Service.; Civil defense--Michigan.; Aging--Study and teaching.; Geriatrics--Michigan--Study and teaching.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Civilian Conservation Corps (U.S.)--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Adult education--Michigan.; Broadcasting--Michigan.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Henderson, William D., b. 1866.; Maddy, Joseph E. (Joseph Edgar), 1891-1966.; Soop, Everett J., 1901-; University of Michigan. Extension Service.; Civil defense--Michigan.; Fire prevention--Study and teaching.; Horace H. Rackham Educational Memorial (Detroit, Mich.)
Contributors:
Fisher, Charles Asbury, 1885-1948.; Henderson, William D., b. 1866.; Soop, Everett J., 1901-; Storey, Alfred W.; Follo, Charles (Charles L.), 1905-1979
Genre/Form:
College publications.; Photographs.
- Director's Office Files
  The Director's Office Files, dated 1912-1994, include the Extension Service's annual reports, minutes of the executive committee and staff meetings, financial records, enrollment records, and topical files. Also included are specific reports and surveys and the personal files of the first three directors: William D. Henderson, Charles A. Fisher, and Everett J. Soop. The bulk of material in the Director's Office Files are the Topical Files. There are four separate runs of topical files: 1912-1959, 1959-1972, ca. 1936-1980 and 1950-1994. The topical files are arranged alphabetically. Some of the more important files concern adult education, Extension Service conferences and institutes, civil defense and disaster training, and the Michigan Coordinating Council of State College Field Services.
  - Annual Reports 1910-1979/80
    - 1910-1931/32 (Box 1)
    - 1932/33-1935/36 (Box 1)
    - 1936/37-1939/40, 1941/42-1944/45 (Box 1)
    - 1946/47-1947/48 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1950/51, 1951/52 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1964/65-1968/69 (Box 1)
    - 1971/72-1976/77 (Box 1)
    - 1977/78-1979/80 (Box 1)
  - Special Reports and Surveys
    - Extension Service of the University of Michigan 1947-1948 (Office of the Provost) (Box 2)
    - Special Report December 1949 (Box 2)
    - Decade of Change 1956 (Box 2)
    - Definition of General Extension Program 1955 (Box 2)
    - University Extension Service 1956 (Box 2)
    - A View of Extension Services In Michigan 1958 (Box 2)
    - Survey of Extension Service Supervisors 1957 (Box 2)
    - Survey: Extramural Courses for Academic Credit (Box 2)
    - Summary of Courses Offered, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Courses for Academic Credit Offered Through Extension Divisions (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Extension (Summary of Findings and Conclusions) 1963 (Box 2)
    - Courses for Academic Credit Offered Through Extension Services, Preliminary Report 1963 (Box 2)
    - Extension Service Self-Survey 1963, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Self-Survey Related Documents 1963 (Box 2)
    - Liberal Arts Degree Programs for Part-Time Students 1964 (Box 2)
    - Survey: Project Extension 1969
      - Dearborn-Detroit (Box 2)
      - Flint-Grand Rapids (Box 2)
      - Oakland Co.-Port Huron-Saginaw (Box 2)
    - Report of the Planning Committee on Extension and Adult Education 1970 (Box 2)
    - Historical Files Committee (Box 2)
    - "Courses for Academic Credit" Preliminary Report 1963 (Box 50)
    - "The Feasibility of an External Degree Program Among the Members Institutions of the Michigan Council of State College Presidents," 1973(?) (Box 50)
    - "Extending Opportunities for Graduate Studies in Michigan," 1977 (Box 50)
    - "Needs Assessment for Continuing Education in Public Health In Michigan," 1980 (Box 50)
    - "A Study of Credit Extension Student: Fall 1980" (Box 50)
  - Minutes
    - Executive Committee
      - List of Committee Members 1928-1968 (Box 2)
      - 1944-1945 (Box 2)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 2)
      - 1947-1949 (Box 2)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 2)
      - 1951-1955 (Box 3)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 3)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 3)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 3)
      - Executive Committee 1976-1981 (Box 50)
        (also includes some correspondence, rosters of committee members, and miscellaneous reports)
    - Staff Meetings
      - 1946-1950 (Box 3)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 3)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 3)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 3)
      - 1956-1960 (Box 3)
      - 1960 (Box 3)
      - 1961-1966 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - 1973-1976 (Box 3)
    - Coordinating Council for Continuing Higher Education
      - Minutes, Correspondence, etc. (in bound volumes)
        - 1970-1972 (Box 53)
        - 1973-1976 (Box 53)
        - 1976-1979 (Box 53)
        - 1979-1983 (Box 53)
  - Financial Records
    - Journal 1912-1915 (Box 3)
    - Budgets
      - 1913/1914-1932/1933 (Box 4)
      - 1932-1937/1938 (Box 4)
      - 1938/1939-1941/1942 (Box 4)
      - 1942/1943-1944/1945 (Box 4)
      - 1945/1946-1946/1947 (Box 4)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 4)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 4)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 4)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 4)
      - 1951/1952-1953/1954 (Box 4)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 4)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 4)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 4)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 4)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 5)
      - 1959-1960, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 50)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 50)
      - 1980/81 (Box 50)
      - 1982/83 (Box 50)
      - 1983/84 (Box 50)
      - 1985/86 (Box 50)
      - 1986/87 (Box 50)
  - Enrollment Records
    - Course Enrollments, Summary Statistics
      - 1913-1944/1945 (Box 5)
      - 1945/1946-1946/1947 (Box 5)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
      - 1948/1949-1949/1950 (Box 5)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 5)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 5)
      - 1952/1953-1953/1954 (Box 5)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 5)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 5)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 5)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 5)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 5)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 5)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - Course Enrollments, Final Summary Statistics 1945-1961 (Box 6)
    - Course Program, Eighth Week Enrollment Statistics
      - 1959-1960 (Box 6)
      - 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 6)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 6)
      - 1963-1964, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1965-1966, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1966-1967, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1968 (Box 6)
    - Course Program Office Reorganization and Review 1957-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Policy and Administrative Material
    - Memos and Administrative Documents
      - 1913-1959 (Box 6)
      - 1960 (Box 6)
    - Administrative Duties and Functions (Box 6)
    - Material on Policy (Box 6)
  - Personal Files
    - William D. Henderson
      - Correspondence
        - 1913-1921 (Box 6)
        - 1922-1933 (Box 6)
      - Speeches (includes text of interview, 1932) (Box 6)
    - Charles A. Fisher
      - Correspondence
        - 1932-1946 (Box 7)
        - 1947-1948 (Box 7)
      - Radio Talks
        - 1933-1947 (Box 7)
        - undated (Box 7)
    - Everett J. Soop
      - Correspondence
        - 1938-1948, 3 folders (Box 7)
        - 1949-1951 (Box 7)
        - 1952-1954 (Box 7)
        - 1955-1958 (Box 7)
      - Rotary Club of Ann Arbor (Box 7)
      - Speeches (Box 7)
    - Harold M. Dorr (Dean of State-wide Education)
      - 1956-1960 (Box 50)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 50)
  - Topical Files 1912-1959
    - Adult Education
      - Programs for Adult Education 1933-1950 (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous 1933-1946, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Non-Public School Phases of Adult Education 1948 (Box 7)
      - Appraisal of University Extension and Adult Education 1948 (Box 8)
      - Public Schools in Michigan 1948-1954 (Box 8)
      - Curriculum Planning Committee 1947-1951 (Box 8)
      - Division of Adult Education, Wayne State University/University of Michigan 1957-1959, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Fund for Adult Education 1951-1961 (Box 8)
    - Adult Education Association of Michigan
      - Administrative Files 1954-1959, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Committee on State Agencies and Organizations 1958 (Box 8)
      - Leadership Training Committee 1957-1959 (Box 8)
      - Legislative Policy Committee 1956-1957 (Box 8)
      - Topics 1954-1958 (Box 8)
    - Aging
      - Curtis, Dr. Henry S. 1940-1953 (Box 8)
      - Institute for Human Adjustment 1948-1949 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence 1950-1954 (Box 8)
      - Third Annual Institute on "Living in the Later Years," Ann Arbor 1950 (Box 8)
    - Alumni University (Box 8)
    - Ann Arbor Adult Education Council 1944-1945 (Box 9)
    - Ann Arbor Council of Social Agencies 1950 (Box 9)
    - Ann Arbor Programs 1944-1947, 1956-1957 (Box 9)
    - Architecture and Design, College of (Box 9)
    - Association of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities; National University Extension Association Committee (cont.)
      - Executive Committee 1953-1956 (Box 9)
      - Atomic Energy Exhibits 1951-1953
        - Correspondence (Box 9)
        - Manual (Box 9)
      - Atoms for Peace 1956 (Box 9)
    - Bruce, Dr. James D.; Vice-President in Charge of University Relations (Box 9)
    - Bruce Adult Education Fund (Box 9)
    - Business Administration, School of (Box 9)
    - Civil Defense 1957-1959 (Box 9)
    - Civilian Conservation Camps, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Community Adult Education (Box 9)
    - Community Councils-W.G. Robinson (1948-1953)
      - Area Conference Reports and Correspondence (Box 9)
      - A-G, including Bay City (Box 9)
      - H-K, including Houghton and Howell (Box 9)
      - L-O, including Lapeer and Manistique (Box 9)
      - P-Z, including Petoskey and Traverse City (Box 9)
    - Conferences and Institutes (Box 10)
      - Adult Education Institutes
        - 1931-1933 (Box 10)
        - 1934-1935 (Box 10)
        - 1936-1939 (Box 10)
        - 1940-1944 (Box 10)
        - 1945-1951 (Box 10)
        - 1952-1957 (Box 10)
      - Aging, Conference or Institute on
        - 1950-1952 (Box 10)
        - 1953-1955, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Airplane Icing Conference 1953 (Box 10)
      - Assessing Officers Conference 1955 (Box 10)
      - ASTE Regional Conference 1954 (Box 10)
      - Boy Scout Explorer Vocational Conference 1953 (Box 10)
      - Bruce Fund Institute 1949-1952, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Building Officials 1955 (Box 10)
      - Carbide Tool Maintenance 1953 (Box 10)
      - Church's Ministry to the Campus 1955 (Box 10)
      - Citizenship Conference 1952-1955 (Box 10)
      - Coal Utilization Conference (Box 11)
        - 1937, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - 1940 (Box 11)
        - 1941 (Box 11)
        - 1942 (Box 11)
      - Concrete Conference (Box 11)
      - Conservation Institute
        - 1935 (Box 11)
        - 1941 (Box 11)
        - 1952-1954 (Box 11)
      - Consumer Finance Management 1953 (Box 11)
      - Department of Commerce Conference 1953 (Box 11)
      - Driver Education Institute 1955 (Box 11)
      - Fishing Clinic 1955 (Box 11)
      - Foremen's Conference
        - 1932-1950 (Box 11)
        - 1952-1955 (Box 11)
      - Group Participation Conference 1952 (Box 11)
      - Hardware Sales Course 1952-1955 (Box 11)
      - Hematology 1952-1954 (Box 11)
      - Home Planners Institute 1944-1946 (Box 11)
      - Law Enforcement Officers 1934-1936 (Box 11)
      - Marriage and Family Living Institute 1945 (Box 11)
      - Merchandising Conference 1953-1955 (Box 11)
      - Methods Time Measurement 1954 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Aeronautical Conference 1955 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Highway Conference 1952-1955 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Pastors Conference 1952-1955 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Regional Foundry Conference 1952-1954 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Rehabilitation Association 1953 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Retailers' Association 1952 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Rural Health Conference 1952 (Box 11)
      - Midwest Music Conference 1957 (Box 11)
      - Motor Vehicle Fleet Supervisor Training 1951-1953 (Box 11)
      - Our Community Tomorrow 1952 (Box 11)
      - Parent Education Institute
        - 1933, 1935, 1940 (Box 11)
        - 1942-1943, 1949-1953 (Box 11)
      - Pharmacy Lectures 1953 (Box 11)
      - Problems of Taxation 1940 (Box 11)
      - Program Planners 1950-1956 (Box 12)
      - Psychology Conference 1951 (Box 12)
      - Quality Control by Statistical Methods 1952-1955 (Box 12)
      - Religious Radio and TV 1953 (Box 12)
      - Retail and Office 1953 (Box 12)
      - School Board Conference 1952-1955 (Box 12)
      - Speech Communication 1953 (Box 12)
      - Teachers of Auto Mechanics 1953-1955 (Box 12)
      - Trouble Shooting in the Woodworking Industry 1952-1955 (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous 1931-1959 (Box 12)
    - Conservation Workshop on Teacher Education 1951 (Box 12)
    - Cook, Richard (Field Representative; Bureau of Business Research) 1952 (Box 12)
    - Cooperative Guidance Program (Box 12)
    - Correspondence Study
      - Historical Study (Box 12)
      - 1936-1941 (Box 12)
      - 1942-1945 (Box 12)
      - 1946-1953 (Box 12)
    - Dean's Conference (Minutes re Extension Courses) 1947 (Box 12)
    - Detroit Federal Tax Committee 1951 (Box 12)
    - Detroit Rackham Educational Memorial Building 1939-1952, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Detroit Retailing Program 1953 (Box 12)
    - Development Council, University of Michigan 1959 (Box 12)
    - Dickerman, Watson (Box 12)
    - Donahue, Wilma, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Education, School of 1946-1958 (Box 12)
    - Engineering, College of 1953-1959 (Box 12)
    - Engineering, Courses 1957 (Box 12)
    - Engineering Research Institute 1954-1957 (Box 12)
    - Engineering Science and War Training 1941-1954 (Box 12)
    - Engineering Technical Institutes 1957-1958 (Box 12)
    - Fire College; Firemanship Training Program 1946, 1950-1956, 4 folders (Box 12)
      (audiotape history of Fire College in box 62)
    - Fisher, C. A., Memorial Fund 1948-1954 (Box 13)
    - Freshman College Teaching Program
      - Correspondence 1934-1936 (Box 13)
      - Teaching Credentials 1934-1935 (Box 13)
      - Textbook and Reading Lists 1934-1936 (Box 13)
    - Garlough, Raymond 1948-1951 (Box 13)
    - Graduate School 1933-1943 (Box 13)
    - Grand Rapids Forum on Aging 1953 (Box 13)
    - Hillsdale College 1951-1959 (Box 13)
    - History Department-Albert Hyma 1954 (Box 13)
    - Hochrein, Bess 1953 (Box 13)
    - Hormel, Olive Deane 1938-1942 (Box 13)
    - International Center 1945 (Box 13)
    - Joint Committee on Institutional Projects 1952-1955 (Box 13)
    - Knappen, Marshall 1956 (Box 13)